[Music]
an impressive number of studies have
shown that lifestyle is the root cause
of what ails us particularly for chronic
conditions
the studies also show that changing
one's lifestyle can have a dramatic
effect on health improvement both in the
prevention and treatment of disease
so given the benefits of lifestyle
medicine interventions it would seem
that our health care system would rush
to embrace this movement
however little could be further from the
truth
now i know we have a for-profit health
care system but even just from a dollars
and cents perspective
it may make sense and dollars
a majority of americans have health care
insurance through their employers
the cost for which is rising and
alarming rate health insurance premiums
continue to go up year after year
unfortunately all the money we're
spending has not translated into
healthier employees or healthier
americans we spend more on health care
per person by far yet the u.s population
is not
healthy by 2014 our life expectancy had
slipped down to 43rd in the world
and since then our life expectancy
declined year after year
it's not just that other countries are
doing better we now may be living
shorter and shorter lives and
unhealthier lives again even just from a
financial bottom line perspective
hundreds of billions in productivity
lost beyond all the health care costs
one employee gets diabetes and it costs
about 10 000 more per year so if a
self-insured company could prevent or
reverse that they could save the company
a lot of money raising the possibility
that workplace wellness programs could
not just be cost neutral in other words
pay for themselves but actually save the
company money even make the company
money this brings up the concept of roi
a return on investment that's how much
money you get back for every dollar
spent so an roi of three to one means
every dollar you spend yields three
dollars back so by investing in such a
program you'd end up tripling your money
you don't know though until you
put it to the test
johnson and johnson for example claimed
that investing in employee wellness
yielded around two to four dollars for
each dollar they spent citibank
estimated their return on investment was
five dollars saved for every dollar
spent
a compilation of a handful of such
studies found an average roi of more
than three dollars of health care cost
savings for every dollar spent on health
promotion a more recent review including
more than 20 studies came up with a
return on investment exceeding five to
one though an even more recent review
out of harvard looking at more than 30
studies found the roi closer to three
dollars spend one dollar get three back
not a bad deal
one heavy manufacturing company report
an outstanding 34-1
return on investment and that's just
direct health care costs
some of their indirect costs like lost
work days and disability fell even more
then you can imagine other potential
benefits happier employees more
productive employees make them more
likely to stick around so do companies
that invest in health promotion have a
competitive advantage publicly traded
companies that got corporate health
achievement awards outperformed the s p
500 by 40 percent
see everett coupe award winners
outperformed the s p 500 2-1
those scoring higher on workplace health
promotion best practices same trend and
the same thing most recently with
companies investing in an internal
culture of health
of course instead of healthier employees
leading to a more profitable company
maybe more profitable companies have
more money to spend to make employees
healthier is there a link between stock
market price growth and having a great
employee wellness program
maybe but correlation doesn't mean
causation maybe prioritizing wellness is
just a sign of a great management team
and that's the real reason they're
raking in the dough
even most of the roi studies lacked an
adequate control group you can't just
compare the cost of employees that
signed up versus those who didn't
because maybe healthier people are just
drawn to such programs in the first
place
that's why you need to randomize
clinical trials to really put it to the
test
which we'll cover
next
[Music]
you